Hello and welcome to Biodose Tools User Guide
This video explains how to fit a dose-effect curve for dicentrics
using as input a .txt file or an Excel file
A .txt file looks like this
The first column indicates the doses
to which I've irradiated the blood samples
and the rest of columns the number of cells
with 0, 1 or more dicentrics
The Excel file looks similar
In the first column you see the doses
and the following columns are
the cells with 0, 1, 2 or more dicentrics
To perform the fitting, open RStudio to run Biodose Tools
To run Biodose Tools, type biodosetools::run_app()
on the R console and press Enter
Once Biodose Tools has loaded
click on "Dicentrics" on the sidebar and choose "Fitting"
Then, click on "Load data from file", and click on "Browse"
Select the .txt/.data file you want to load
Click on "Generate table" to load the data into Biodose Tools
Click on "Calculate parameters" to calculate
N, X, mean, var, DI, and the u-value
Note that overdispersed u-values are highlighted in red
Then, choose the linear or the linear-quadratic fitting formula
Lastly, select the fitting model
(the recommended option is "Automatic")
To perform the fitting, click on "Calculate fitting"
The fitting results can be seen if you scroll down
The results contain the fitting parameters, fitting coefficients,
summary statistics, and dose-effect fitting curve
To save the results click on "Save fitting data"
and select the directory where you want to save the .rds file
The .rds format is used by Biodose Tools
to perform dose estimations from your fitting curve
Now we will repeat the process with an Excel file
First of all, make sure to uncheck the "Load data from a file" option
Check the number of doses and
the maximum number of dicentrics per cell
and make sure they match your data
You can change these values manually
Click on "Generate table" to create an empty table
Copy the doses from your Excel file
and paste them under D (Gy) on the table
Copy the information of the cells from your Excel file
and paste it under C0 on the table
And now follow the same steps as before